STEPHEN BYARD

SOFTWARE DEVELOPER







Nashville, TN 37206



stephen-byard



sbyardnss

ABOUT ME

I have spent most of my career as a designer and senior editor for a nationwide real estate marketing startup where I learned how to find quick solutions on the fly and develop cost-effective processes for long term implementation. My experience has provided me with a strong level of confidence in myself but also allowed me to internalize the team based mindset where the birth of effective solutions takes place. Having made the switch to software development, I find myself on a path which merges the skills gathered from my previous experience with my passion for logic and creative expression.

Whether it be music, film, or visual arts, the process of piecing together elements in a meaningful manner never fails to satisfy. From my earliest forays into software development, I found the process of writing quality code similarly appealing. Heavily drawn to the puzzle-like nature and acutely aware of its endless complexity, I am always on the lookout for opportunities to grow, learn, and solve ever more challenging problems.

SKILLS

JavaScript | TypeScript | React | Vue Angular | Python | Django | HTML CSS | Bootstrap | Adobe Suite | SQL SCRUM | Content Management

PROJECTS

VILLAGER CHESS



villager-client



villager-server

Deployed Application

CARSELLO ART



carsello-client



carsello-server

Deployed Application

EDUCATION

CERTIFICATE, SOFTWARE DEVELOPMENT

Nashville Software School 2023

BA. COMMUNICATION

University of Tennessee at Chattanooga 2013

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

ENGINEERING INTERN

Chess.com | October 2023 - Present

Full-time internship program working as part of Front End Development team in planning/implementation of new technologies and refactoring of previous applications.

- Created MVC applications utilizing VueJS with TypeScript
- Managed/adjusted Twig files for PHP compile
- Developed testing suites using Cypress
- Planned and coordinated projects with management and design teams
- Daily SCRUM workflow
- Docker DevOps and environment setup/management
- Ticketing via Jira/Atlassian
- Source code/version control with Git/Github
- Assisted in migration from Vue 2 to Vue 3 for future rollout

SOFTWARE DEVELOPER

Nashville Software School | Jan 2023 - Jun 2023

Intensive full-time, six months software development bootcamp focusing on Python/Django development fundamentals and problem solving. The final three months of the program being executed in a simulated company environment with SCRUM methodology.

- Daily hands on application of OOP fundamentals through group and individual projects
- Created single page applications in JavaScript, regularly utilizing the React framework
- Source code/version control with Git/Github
- Solution Design: white-boarding and wireframes
- Leveraged Django for creating and editing server-generated web applications
- Created RESTful API's with Django REST framework
- Retrieved and stored database information with SQLite
- Practiced testing with Python's unit test framework

GRAPHIC DESIGNER / SHIFT SUPERVISOR

HouseLens.com

June 2015 - December 2022

Junior designer | March 2016 - June 2017

Contract | June 2015 - December 2015